to give a first example of why multithreaded
processes and writing applications that can
run in parallel is challenging let's look at
this question let's assume we have a program
initially it was designed to run on a single core
but now we buy 100 cores and we want to make it
more efficient so what we do is that we start
writing the code and we do a nice job eventually
we end up with only 25 percent of the initial
program so one every four lines that cannot be
executed in parallel if we now run this with one
hundred cores how many times faster will this program be?
the answer to that is in between one
and ten so actually it turns out that you can
get a limit or an upper bound on how much your
parallel process can be faster compared to the
sequential one or serial one using
Amdahl's law
if you see the speed up it's always less than or
equal to this formula so here you have one divided
s which is the portion that is not parallel plus
the portion that is parallel that gets smaller
and smaller with the higher number of cores
you use which in this case is n if you use
an infinite number of cores then this component
here disappears and what you are left with it's
one divided s that is the limit for the speed up s
in our example is 25% which means that this program
will never be faster than four times its serial
counterpart no matter how many cores you use
so the serial portion of an application has
disproportionate effects on the performance
gained by adding additional cores and with this you
can actually compute which is the maximum speed up